Guide to the St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program records
1973-1996
MS 1730
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The records include administrative records, writings, an oral history, photographs, and memorabilia pertaining to the St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program.
St. Luke's Hospital Center. St. Luke's Palliative Care Program
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Patrice O'Connor, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Separated Materials
AC13 Oral history [from interview with Patrice O'Connor and Carleton Sweetser], 2 tapes Audio Cassette (D60)
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Organizational Records, 1973-1990, II. Writings, 1975-1996, III. Photographs and Memorabilia, 1974-1990.
Biographical / Historical
Planning for the St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program began in 1973 with the formation of the Hospice at St. Luke's Committee, chaired by the Reverend Carleton Sweetser. By 1975, the group had raised the necessary funds to initiate a pilot project which became St. Luke's Hospice. In 1980, Patrice O'Connor was appointed as the first and only hospice team coordinator. The hospice team sought to augment the medical care given to terminally ill patients by focusing on pain control and disease symptom management. St. Luke's Hospice was the second hospice program in the United States, and the first to be incorporated into an existing medical center. The hospice committee and team developed a method of care which provided several services for their patients, including in-patient care, home care, clinical consulting, and bereavement counseling for families. Their approach came to be known as the "scatterbed method," which was modeled by several hospice programs developed throughout the United States. The hospice also served as an educational center for the hospice movement, hosting several workshops and conferences on hospice issues. In 1986, the hospice changed its name to the St. Luke's Palliative Care Program, to reflect the wide variety of services provided and to comply with changing state regulations. The program was forced to close in 1990 due to hospital center funding cuts.
Biographical / Historical
Planning for the hospice program at St. Luke's Hospital Center in New York, New York formally began in 1973 with the formation of the Hospice at St. Luke's Committee, chaired by the Reverend Carleton Sweetser. The goal of the committee was to establish a program for the treatment of the terminally ill which augmented the medical care given to these patients in the hospital by focusing on pain control and management of disease symptoms. Using funding provided by outside sources, most notably the United Thank Offering of the Women of the Episcopal Church, the committee hired a staff and began a pilot project in 1975 which became St. Luke's Hospice. In 1980, the hospice began to get two-thirds of its funding from the budget of St. Luke's Hospital Center. At this time, Patrice O'Connor was appointed as the first hospice team coordinator, a position she held until the closing of the program.
St. Luke's Hospice was the second hospice established in the United States and the first to be incorporated into an existing medical center. The methods developed by the hospice team were directly influenced and inspired by the work of Cicely Saunders and St. Christopher's Hospice in London, England. The approach St. Luke's developed provided several services to patients and their families including in-patient care, home care, clinic care, and bereavement counseling. This system of providing palliative care in several different locations both in and out of the medical center came to be known as the "scatterbed method," and was modeled by many hospice programs established throughout the United States.
The St. Luke's Hospice also became well known as an educational center for hospice training. Members of the hospice team routinely gave presentations at conferences and published articles in professional journals. The hospice also held many workshops, and in 1984 they hosted a series of thirteen half-day conferences devoted to hospice care for cancer patients.
In 1986, the name of the hospice was changed to St. Luke's Palliative Care Program to reflect the broad range of services provided and to comply with changes in the New York State Department of Health and Human Services regulations. Throughout the years, the Hospice/Palliative Care Program received many awards, including the Mayor's Volunteer Service Award and the Eleanor Roosevelt Community Service Award, both in 1984. The Palliative Care Program closed in 1990 as the result of hospital center funding cuts.
Scope and Contents
The records include administrative records, writings, an oral history, photographs, and memorabilia pertaining to the St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program.
Hospice care -- United States; Hospices (Terminal care); Palliative treatment; Terminal care; O'Connor, Patrice M.; Sweetser, Carleton J.; St. Luke's Hospital Center. St. Luke's Hospice; St. Luke's Hospital Center. St. Luke's Palliative Care Program
- Organizational Records, 1973-1996
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged in alphabetical order by type of record, Organizational Records includes meeting minutes, memoranda, proposals, reports, grant files, brochures and other materials which document the administrative functioning of the St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program. Minutes from the meetings of the Hospice at St. Luke's Committee comprise a substantial section of the series.
  - Brochures, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conference brochures, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum vitae of hospice team members [Rev. Carleton J. Sweetser, Patrice O'Connor, Roberta Paige, Rev. David M. Pyle], Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Grant materials
    - Susan Greenwall Foundation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - National Institute of Health [funding not obtained], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - United Thank Offering, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Women's Hospital Division, Ladies Assistant Board, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hospice Demonstration Program, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hospice at St. Luke's Committee
    General
    In 1980, the committee name was changed to Hospice Advisory Committee; in 1986, it was changed to Palliative Care Advisory Committee.
    - Hospice Pilot Project summary, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Memoranda, 1973-1974, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, 1973-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11-19)
    - Proposals, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Subcommittee on Education, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Subcommittee on Organization and Job Description, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Reports and statistics, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Writings, 1975-1996
  Writings contains articles about St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program, articles by members of the hospice team, and a transcript and tapes from an oral history dictated by Patrice O'Connor and Rev. Carleton Sweetser. Writings by hospice team members cover many topics relevant to St. Luke's Hospice/Palliative Care Program and to the hospice movement in general.
  - Oral history [from interview with Patrice O'Connor and Rev. Carleton Sweetser], 1996
    - Transcript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Tapes
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
      - Tape 1 of 2 (Box 4)
      - Tape 2 of 2 (Box 5)
  - Articles, 1975-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Writings by hospice team members
    - O'Connor, Patrice, 1986-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Other team members, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photographs and Memorabilia, 1974-1990
  Photographs and Memorabilia includes materials from anniversaries, award ceremonies, and conferences. The series also contains several photographs of hospice team members, volunteers, and patients. Individuals included in the photographs include the Reverend Carleton Sweetser, Patrice O'Connor, Roberta Paige, Maria Machuca, Judith Gantley, and Dr. Richard Geltman.
  - Anniversaries
    - Fifth [photographs], 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Tenth [photographs], 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fifteenth
      - Address by Dr. Tom West, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Invitation and bulletin from "Service of Thanksgiving", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Photographs, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Awards
    - Jack C. Massey Foundation Award, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mayor's Volunteer Service Award, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt Community Service Award, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Closing of program [invitation to reception], 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Conferences
    - The Hospice Program: An Interdisciplinary Approach to Terminal Cancer Patients and Families, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - National Hospice Organization, Washington, DC, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - National Hospice Organization, Orlando, Florida, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Doctor's order sheet, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    This depicts first time hospice mentioned in a hospital record.
  - Photographs
    - Hospice patients, 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
    - Hospice team, 1978, 1980, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Hospice volunteers, 1983, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)